Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Currier & Ives Prints 1844-1880 PR 230
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society collection of Currier & Ives prints
1844-1880
New-York Historical Society
Currier & Ives
PR 230
3 Linear feet in 7 flat file folders
About 58 lithographs and chromolithographs produced by Currier & Ives. Principal topics include the patriotism of men, women and children during the Civil War; images of Jesus Christ and Christian saints; Mississippi River paddle steamboats; animals; country landscapes; and "The Life of a Fireman" series of six plates.
Arrangement
Prints are arranged in six folders by size and, roughly, by subject, as follows:
FF1: Civil War soldiers
FF2: Religious
FF3: Certificates and registers
FF4: Miscellaneous
FF5: "Life of a Fireman" plates
FF6: Miscellaneous (steamboats, landscapes, etc)
FF7: Miscellaneous (children, animals, etc.)
Biographical / Historical
Currier & Ives was a successful American printmaking firm headed by Nathaniel Currier (1813-1888) and James Merritt Ives (1824-1895). Based in New York City from 1834 to 1907, the prolific firm produced prints from paintings by fine artists as black and white lithographs that were hand colored. The name Currier & Ives first appeared in 1857, when Currier invited James Merritt Ives, the company's bookkeeper and accountant, to become his partner. Currier died in 1888; Ives remained active in the firm until his death in 1895. Both Currier's and Ives's sons followed their fathers in the business, which was eventually liquidated in 1907. (Source: Library of Congress authorities record)
Conditions Governing Access
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was compiled by New-York Historical Society from various donations and purchases. Known acquisition dates or sources are noted at the item level.
Related Materials
This collection includes a relatively small portion of N-YHS's total holdings of Currier & Ives prints. In addition to this collection, N-YHS holds about 900 Currier & Ives prints across 10 other collections, which are organized by format, subject, collector, or other focus in the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections (PPAC). An item level list of the Currier & Ives prints in all PPAC collections is available on request via email. Contact printroom@nyhistory.org.
Scope and Contents
The collection holds about 58 lithographs and chromolithographs produced by Currier & Ives, with some by Nathaniel Currier dating before his partnership with James Ives. (N-YHS holds about 900 Currier & Ives prints across several collections; see the Related Materials Note in this finding aid.) Principal topics in this collection include the patriotism of men, women and children during the Civil War; images of Jesus Christ and Christian saints; Mississippi River paddle steamboats; animals; and country landscapes. There is a complete set of six plates for the series "The Life of a Fireman." A few images concern commentary or satire on political or social matters. There is a marriage certificate and a family photograph registry, unusual formats for the Currier & Ives firm.
The container list includes the titles of all items in the collection. A "Peters" catalogue number was recorded in the container list if one was noted on the print.
Certificates.; Chromolithographs; Lithographs.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Pictorial works.; Christian saints -- Pictorial works.; Fire fighters -- Pictorial works.; River boats -- Pictorial works.
- "The Little Recruit", 1863 (Folder FF-1)
  Scope and Contents
  Peters 901. Acquisition: Gift of Daniel Parish, Jr., April 5, 1900.
- "Ole Massa's Grave", undated (Folder FF-1)
  Acquisition: Gift of Daniel Parish, Jr., November 14, 1892.
- "The Union Volunteer", 1861 (Folder FF-1)
- "The Soldier Boy. 'Off Duty'", 1864 (Folder FF-1)
  Peters 908.
- "The Little Zouave. 'Up Boys and at the M'", 1861 (Folder FF-1)
  Peters 904.
- "The Soldier Boys. The Last Defence", undated (Folder FF-1)
- "The Hour of Victory", 1861 (Folder FF-1)
  Peters 898.
- "The Pride of America", undated (Folder FF-1)
- "The Star Spangled Banner", undated (Folder FF-1)
  Peters 921.
- "The Brave Wife", undated (Folder FF-1)
- "The Soldier's Grave", 1862 (Folder FF-1)
- "The Infant Saviour. Le Sauveur du Monde. El Salvador del Mundo", undated (Folder FF-2)
  Acquisition: Purchase, Elie Nadelman; stamped as part of N-YHS Folk Arts Collection, November 17, 1937.
- "Holy Family. La Sagrada Familia", undated (Folder FF-2)
- "The Resurrection", undated (Folder FF-2)
- "Sacred Heart of Mary. Sacre Coeur de Marie. Sacrado Corazon de Maria.", undated (Folder FF-2)
- "Saint Bridget. Sta. Brigida.", undated (Folder FF-2)
- "The Annunciation", 1844 (Folder FF-2)
- "Sacred Heart of Jesus. Sacre Coeur de Jesus. Sagrado Corazon de Jesus.", undated (Folder FF-2)
- "The Descent from the Cross", undated (Folder FF-2)
- "John Wesley Preaching on His Fathers Grave", undated (Folder FF-2)
  Acquisition: Purchase from Plaza Art Galleries, October 31, 1941; item #7 in gallery catalogue of October 30, 1941.
- "Family Photograph Register", undated (Folder FF-3)
  The document is undated. Handwritten entries on the register for G. Henry Rafuse, his wife Frances, their two children and their marriage dates. Dates of births, deaths, and marriages range from 1854-1936. There are no photographs.
- "Marriage Certificate", 1875 (Folder FF-3)
  Certificate is filled out: Abel N. Moore and Isanah A. Baker, both of Moscow, Maine, married October 16, 1870.
- "The Exquisite. The 'Pet of the Ladies'", undated (Folder FF-4)
  Acquisition: Likely a gift from Daniel Parish, Jr., September 27, 1901.
- "The Momentous Question", 1853 (Folder FF-4)
  Lithographed and published by Nathaniel Currier.
- "The Old Farm House", 1872 (Folder FF-4)
- "Grand Papa's Cane", undated (Folder FF-4)
  Peters 2804.
- "Virtue, Love & Temperance. Love, Purity & Fidelity", 1851 (Folder FF-4)
  By Nathaniel Currier. Acquisition: Gift of Kiliaen Van Rensselaer, January 19, 1946.
- "Grand National Democratic Banner. Press Onward", 1844 (Folder FF-4)
  Lithographed and published by Nathaniel Currier. Political poster for James K. Polk and George M. Dallas. From the Bella C. Landauer Collection.
- "The Cleveland Smile", undated (Folder FF-4)
- "Maiden's Rock. Mississippi River" [Steamboat/paddle wheel], undated (Folder FF-4)
  Purchased, November 15, 1938, Wilbur Fund. Print matted.
- "On the Mississippi" [Steamboat/paddle wheel], 1869 (Folder FF-4)
- "Luke Blackburn, By Bonnie Scotland, Dam Nevada", 1880 (Folder FF-4)
  E. Forbes, del. Acquisition: Gift of Samuel V. Hoffman, December 5, 1924.
- "The Life of a Fireman [Plate 1]: The Night Alarm. 'Start her lively boys'", 1854 (Folder FF-5)
  Acquisition: Gift of Daniel Parish, Jr., April 27, 1899.
- "The Life of a Fireman [Plate 2]: The Race. 'Jump her boys, jump her!'", 1854 (Folder FF-5)
- "The Life of a Fireman [Plate 3]: The Fire. 'Now then with a will - Shake her up, boys!'", 1854 (Folder FF-5)
  2 copies. One copy was a gift of Daniel Parish, Jr., April 27, 1899. The other is stamped "Property of E.A. Cruikshank."
- "The Life of a Fireman [Plate 4]: The Ruins. 'Take up.' - 'Man your rope.'", 1854 (Folder FF-5)
- "The Life of a Fireman [Plate 5]: The New Era. Steam and Muscle", 1861 (Folder FF-5)
  Acquisition: Gift of Daniel Parish, Jr., May 17, 1899.
- "The Life of a Fireman [Plate 6]: The Metropolitan System", 1866 (Folder FF-5)
- Small reproduction of plate 4 "The Life of a Fireman. the Ruins" and publicity material for the Currier & Ives fireman prints., 1884 (Folder FF-5)
  Acquisition: The reproduction was a gift of E. Lawrence Sampter, July 8, 1957. The publicity document was from the I.N. Stokes collection.
- "The Home of Evangeline. 'In the Acadian Land'", 1864 (Folder FF-6)
  F.F. Palmer, del.
- "Gray's Elegy. In a Country Church Yard", 1864 (Folder FF-6)
  F.F. Palmer, del. Label on back reads: Purchased, May 7, 1936, but card in file reads that the item was a gift of Mrs. Eliza J. Watson in memory of her husband, John Jay Watson, 1946.
- "On the Mississippi" [Steamboat/Paddle wheel], 1869 (Folder FF-6)
  Gift of Henry O. Havemeyer, Yale 1900.
- "The Mississippi in Time of Peace", 1865 (Folder FF-6)
- "New England Winter Scene", 1861 (Folder FF-6)
  Painted by Geo. H. Durrie.
- "Enoch Arden - The Lonely Isle", 1869 (Folder FF-6)
- "The Beauties of Billiards. 'A carom on the dark red'", 1869 (Folder FF-6)
  Gift of Peter Laibson and Donald Smith, from the collection of Lillian & Judah Skoal, 2019.
- "Little Snowbird", circa 1868-1878 (Folder FF7)
- "Brother and Sister", 1842 (Folder FF7)
- "Little Mary and Her Lamb", circa 1857-1872 (Folder FF7)
- "Fruits of the Seasons", 1872 (Folder FF7)
- "The Little Favorite", circa 1838-1856 (Folder FF7)
- "Two Little Fraid Cats", circa 1857-1872 (Folder FF7)
- "My Little White Kitties Playing Dominoes", circa 1872-1874 (Folder FF7)
- "Kitties Among the Roses", 1873 (Folder FF7)
- "My Three White Kitties Learning their ABC", circa 1857-1872 (Folder FF7)
- "My Little White Kitties", circa 1857-1872 (Folder FF7)
- "My Kitty and Canary", 1871 (Folder FF7)
- "Little Minnie Taking Tea", 1872 (Folder FF7)